{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "ThisorganizationdeployedtheISAFshortlyaftertheonlytimeithaseverinvokedArticle5.InMarch 2017, opposition leaders in Montenegro wrote to Steve Bannon to ask him to block Montenegro’s accession to this organization. Donald Trump has repeatedly complained that members of this organization are not spending 2 percent of their GDP on defense. For ten points, name this military alliance which consists of the United States, Canada and various European countries.",
      "answer": "North Atlantic Treaty Organization"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city is sometimes grouped together with an opposite river counterpart named after the Van Rensselaer family. A document named after this city inspired the later Galloway Plan. A political cartoon published in support of a plan named for this city depicts a snake in eight segments above the caption “Join or Die.” This city was the site of a 1754 political congress at which Benjamin Franklin proposed a namesake plan of union. For ten points, name this capital city of New York.",
      "answer": [
        "Albany",
        "Albany Plan",
        "Albany Congress"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Over 100 civilians died during Operation Carthage in one of these buildings in Copenhagen when it was struck by RAF bombers as collateral. One of these institutions served as the headquarters for the White Rose anti-Nazi movement in Munich, and another of these institutions was transformed into the S-21 prison camp by the Khmer Rouge. A sacred olive grove dedicated to Athena surrounded an ancient example of one of these institutions founded by Plato. For ten points, name these institutions that include the Lyceum and Plato’s Academy.",
      "answer": [
        "schools",
        "boarding schools, universities, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote a Missa Solemnis mass for Archduke Randolph, his patron. He commemorated theBattleofVitoriawiththepieceWellington’s Victory anddonateditsfundstovictimsofthePeninsular War. This composer allegedly dedicated a piece to Napoleon until the decision to establish an empire prompted this man to rip that piece in half and dedicate it to “the memory of a great man.” For ten points, name this composer of the Emperor piano concerto and the Eroica symphony.",
      "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
    },
    {
      "question": "Though this general was pushed back to Gazala during Operation Crusader, he managed to capture Tobruk from Claude Auchinleck shortly after. This man’s strategy of setting wooden poles to block glider landings led the logs to become known as this man’s “asparagus.” This man was put in charge of defending the Atlantic Wall during D-Day two years after he lost to Bernard Montgomery at the First Battle of El Alamein. For ten points, name this German general whose North African campaigns earned him the nickname “Desert Fox.”",
      "answer": "Erwin Rommel"
    },
    {
      "question": "The sociologist Phil Zuckerman primarily studies societies where this belief is prevalent. John Lennox debated a writer holding this philosophical position in 2008. Baron d’Holbach’s 18th-century book The System of Nature was widely criticized for holding this belief. Another advocate for this philosophical positionargued against itsalternative in 1986’sThe Blind Watchmaker. ChristopherHitchens and Richard Dawkins are among the “Four Horsemen” of, for ten points, what philosophical stance that rejects the existence of God?",
      "answer": [
        "atheism",
        "descriptions of believing there is no God"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This location was the subject of a 2007 controversy when John Fire Lame Deer symbolically planted a prayer staff into the ground. Doane Robinson initially intended for Lewis and Clark to be honored at this site. To work on this project, its sculptor abandoned a relief honoring Jefferson Davis and Stonewall Jackson at Stone Mountain. Gutzon Borglum designed, for ten points, what South Dakota landmark that features the faces of Washington, Lincoln, Roosevelt, and Jefferson?",
      "answer": "Mount Rushmore"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure met an illegitimate Byzantine princess named Bayalan while visiting an Uzbek ruler. This figure was employed as a judge by both the ruler of the Maldives and the Sultan of Delhi. This man criticized the women of Mali for not covering themselves and documented his expedition to China in his Travels, which began after his first pilgrimage to Mecca. For ten points, name this Moroccan traveler that crossed much of the medieval Islamic world.",
      "answer": "Abu Abdallah Muhammad Ibn Battuta"
    },
    {
      "question": "Different ways to do this activity are listed in a “Rag” written by Phil Ochs. David Harris founded an organization that advocated for this action and was symbolized by the letter omega, for ohm. Common methods of doing this included wearing women’s underwear to feign homosexuality, one of a number of ways to get 4-F status. One of Jimmy Carter’s first acts as president was pardoning people who had performed, for ten points, what action by which people avoided fighting in the Vietnam War?",
      "answer": [
        "draft dodging the Vietnam War",
        "synonyms for dodge, including draft evasion and draft avoidance",
        "equivalents such as avoiding military service in Vietnam"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During a power struggle, this man stabbed his former ally, John Comyn, at a monastery in Dumfries. This man’s claim to the throne was defended in a letter to Pope John XXII in the Declaration of Arbroath. This man’s Treaty of Corbeil renewed the Auld Alliance with France, and he assumed the position of Guardian after the defeat at Falkirk of William Wallace. For ten points, name this Scottish king who was defeated the English at the Battle of Bannockburn.",
      "answer": "Robert the Bruce"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A tunnel built in this city connected Dobrinja [doh-brin-ya] and Butmir, allowing civilian escape and the inflow of humanitarian aid. The Markale [mar-kah-lay] massacres occurred in this city, where a battle was triggered by protests in front of a Holiday Inn. Stanislav Gali´c [gall-itch] was convicted of crimes against humanity for his actions in this city. The attacking forces of the Republika Srpska replaced those of the Yugoslav People’s Army in this city, where fighting was ended by the Dayton Accords. For ten points, name this capital city that was brutally besieged during the Bosnian War.",
        "answer": "Siege of Sarajevo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This type of soldier was deployed in Sarajevo, but failed to stop the violence. These forces, drawn from many different nations, wear distinctive blue helmets.",
        "answer": [
          "United Nations peacekeepers or the United Nations Protection Force",
          "UNPROFOR"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1969, Jim Morrison was arrested in this state for alleged indecent exposure at the Dinner Key Auditorium. In 1997, Andrew Cunanan killed designer Gianni Versace [JAHN-ee ver-SOTCH-ee] on the steps of his mansion in this state. Al Capone died at his Palm Island estate in this state, which was the setting of the movie Scarface and a 1980s TV series about a pair of vice cops. For ten points, name this state where the 2000 deportation of Eli´an Gonz´alez led to protests in Little Havana in Miami.",
        "answer": "Miami Beach"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anton Cermak, the mayor of this city, was killed in Miami in 1933 by Giuseppe Zangara in a failed assassination attempt on the newly-inaugurated Franklin D. Roosevelt.",
        "answer": "Chicago"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Liz Carpenter was a staff director under this woman, whose quote “Where flowers bloom, so does hope” was often used in her promotion of the Highway Beautification Act. This author of A White House Diary was married to a president who died of a heart attack five years after deciding not to run for re-election. For ten points, name this woman who became First Lady aboard Air Force One in 1963, the wife of Lyndon Johnson.",
        "answer": [
          "Claudia Alta Johnson",
          "Claudia Alta “Lady Bird” Johnson"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Claudia Johnson was a strong proponent of her husband’s Great Society platform, including this program that provides early childhood education and nutrition support to low-income families.",
        "answer": "Head Start"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader ordered the creation of Unit 101, which committed the Qibya massacre as a reprisal attack. In his later career, he became minister of defense after Pinhas Lavon was caught planning false-flag bombing attacks on Egypt. This leader authorized Operation Magic Carpet to relocate thousands of Yemeni and Ethiopian Jews. He merged the Irgun militia into the IDF to fight against the Arab League shortly after his country gained independence in 1948. For ten points, name the first prime minister of Israel.",
        "answer": "David Ben-Gurion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After his career in politics, Ben-Gurion retired to one of these Israeli collectivist farms, many of which industrialized over the 20th century. A few hundred of these communities exist in Israel today.",
        "answer": "kibbutzim"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This essay quotes from a burial song for Marines to show that a straw man has no more worth than an animal. This essay argues against a similar chapter by William Paley by claiming that expediency is not a sufficient excuse to abstain from revolution. This work wonders what form of government could follow after monarchy and democracy, noting that its author “heartily accepts the motto ‘that government is best which governs least’,” and repeatedly voices opposition to the Mexican War and to slavery. For ten points, name this 1849 essay promoting non-violent protesting by Henry David Thoreau.",
        "answer": "Civil Disobedience or Resistance to Civil Government"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "”Civil Disobedience” was written by Thoreau after he spent a night in jail for refusing to pay this type of duty.",
        "answer": "poll tax"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man conquered Ferrara from his former ally, Alfonso d’Este [DESS-tay], and took personal command during the Siege of Mirandola. This man issued a bull confirming the Treaty of Tordesillas [torr-de-SEE-yes]. This member of the della Rovere [ROH-vay-rey] family was made a cardinal by his uncle, Sixtus IV. This pope formed the League of Cambrai to fight Venice and created the Swiss Guard. For ten points, name this warlike Pope who rebuilt St. Peter’s Basilica and commissioned Michelangelo to paint the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel.",
        "answer": "Pope Julius II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Julius II was succeeded by a Medici pope of this name; his efforts to fund the rebuilding of St Peter’s Basilica were opposed by Martin Luther. A “Great” Pope of this name met Attila outside Rome in 452 AD.",
        "answer": [
          "Pope Leo",
          "Leo X and/or I"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In Roman tradition, these people were the dedicatees of poems called epithalamium and wore a yellow article of clothing called a flammeum. According to a popular theory, Rembrandt painted one of these people being given a necklace and being embraced by a man representing Isaac; that painting is known as “The Jewish [one of these people].” According to some interpretations, a figure in a green dress is one of these people in a painting by Jan van Eyck that also shows the merchant Giovanni Arnolfini. For ten points, name these women who often wear white veils before they are married.",
        "answer": [
          "brides",
          "wife, even after “Jewish” is read",
          "The Jewish Bride",
          "Het Joodse bruidje"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gala was the bride of this painter, who often used her as a model, and she can be seen looking up at Christ in this artist’s Corpus Hypercubus.",
        "answer": "Salvador Dali"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Snyder, a member of this group, got stabbed by a colleague for beating Milt Elliott’s ox. A separated branch of this group was aided by the Miwok Tribe after leaving Truckee Lake and was known as the “Forlorn Hope.” James Reed was a leader of this group, which made the mistake of taking the Hasting Cutoff, trapping them during a harsh 1846 winter in the Sierra Nevadas en route to California. For ten points, name this group of pioneers that infamously turned to cannibalism.",
        "answer": [
          "Donner Party",
          "equivalent descriptions, like the Donner group"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Instead of going north through modern Idaho, the Hastings Cutoff taken by the Donner Party cuts through the Great Salt Lake Desert, a region filled with salt flats that was once this prehistoric lake.",
        "answer": [
          "Lake Bonneville",
          "Bonneville Salt Flats"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "20th Century Culinary History",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Snack food popularized by the Cretors family, Orville Redenbacher, and countless movie theaters.",
          "answer": "popcorn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trademarked term for a pre-packaged frozen meal, invented by the Swanson company in 1953.",
          "answer": "TV dinner"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kentucky businessman whose pressure fryer-based secret recipe launched the KFC franchise.",
          "answer": "Colonel Harlan Sanders"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fictional character invented in 1921, a woman that names a widespread cookbook series and brand of baking goods.",
          "answer": [
            "Betty Crocker",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former KFC cook and franchisee who founded Wendy’s in 1969.",
          "answer": "Dave Thomas"
        },
        {
          "question": "TV chef, author of the 1961 cookbook Mastering the Art of French Cooking, whose kitchen is now in the Smithsonian.",
          "answer": "Julia Child"
        },
        {
          "question": "Entrepreneur who opened the first franchised McDonald’s store in 1955 in Illinois.",
          "answer": "Ray Kroc"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of Adventures in Good Eating, a mid-century list of quality restaurants, whose name is now a popular brand of cake mixes.",
          "answer": "Duncan Hines"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Alexander the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Kingdom that Alexander the Great ruled, to the north of classical Greece.",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Macedon",
            "Macedonia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Tutor of Alexander, a student of Plato.",
          "answer": "Aristotle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire to the east that Alexander the Great conquered. It used a system of local government called satrapies.",
          "answer": "Persian Empire or Achaemenid Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rival leader of that empire, who was killed after Alexander won at Issus and Gaugamela.",
          "answer": "Darius III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Alexander the Great who implemented longer spears known as sarissas.",
          "answer": "Philip II"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that Alexander the Great besieged, by building a causeway into the Mediterranean.",
          "answer": "Tyre"
        },
        {
          "question": "338 BC battle in Boeotia where Alexander led the cavalry to defeat an Athenian alliance of Greek cities.",
          "answer": "Battle of Chaeronea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle where Alexander defeated King Porus of the Paurava kingdom. It led to the annexation of the Punjab, Alexander’s most eastern conquest.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Hydaspes River"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mesopotamian Artwork",
      "prompt": "What...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "River, along with the Euphrates, provided Mesopotamia with the sustenance required to produce artwork?",
          "answer": "Tigris River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Terrorist organization based in Raqqa has destroyed many ancient artworks?",
          "answer": [
            "ISIS or Islamic State of Iraq and Syria",
            "or ISIL",
            "or Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant",
            "or Daesh"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Stepped pyramids were common in Mesopotamian cites?",
          "answer": "ziggurats"
        },
        {
          "question": "Babylonian king is being given a rod by Shamash in a stele [stee-lee] on display at the Louvre?",
          "answer": "Hammurabi"
        },
        {
          "question": "City was the site of a “White Temple” and is the legendary home of Gilgamesh?",
          "answer": "Uruk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Blue gate showing dragons and bulls now resides in a German museum?",
          "answer": "Ishtar Gate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Blue stone was frequently imported from central Asia for artistic use?",
          "answer": "lapis lazuli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Creature with the head of a man and the body of a winged ox was frequently sculpted by the Assyrians?",
          "answer": "lamassu"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Knowledge of this text was greatly advanced with the discovery of the Mawangdui silk manuscripts and the Guodian slips. This text, which compares “ruling a large state” to (20 pts)",
        "“boiling a delicate fish,” was allegedly produced when a guard asked its author to share his wisdom before leaving the country on a water buffalo. It notes that a wise leader practices “inaction, and the people look after themselves” and begins with the assertion that the (10 pts)",
        "Way is nameless. For ten points, name this text allegedly penned by Lao Tzu, the principal text of Daoism."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tao Te Ching or Daodejing",
        "Laozi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A geologic formation within this state includes the Ozona Arch and Val Verde Basin, and its Yates Oil Field is located west of the Edwards Plateau in this state’s (20 pts)",
        "Trans-Pecos. In the 1920s, the Cowden Field turned this state’s cities of Odessa and Midland in the oil-producing Permian Basin into boom towns. The nation’s largest refinery is found at (10 pts)",
        "Port Arthur here, and a salt dome in this state near Beaumont was the site of the Spindletop gusher in 1901. For ten points, many oil companies such as ConocoPhilips are headquartered in what state’s largest city of Houston?"
      ],
      "answer": "Texas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) James Morrison was pardoned for his role in this event, whose instigator, according to legend, wore a lead plummet during it to provide a quick avenue to suicide. The HMS Pandora was sent to (20 pts)",
        "investigate this event, but ended up sinking in the Torres Strait. John Adams was the only survivor of a group that, during this event, settled on (10 pts)",
        "Pitcairn Island after serving on a ship delivering breadfruit. Fletcher Christian led, for ten points, what 1789 insurrection on board William Bligh’s Royal Navy ship?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "mutiny on the HMS Bounty",
        "equivalent descriptions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Edward Snowden revealed, among many other things, that the NSA program “Penetrating Hard Targets” is funded to build these devices. Researches at UC Berkeley doubt whether D-Wave’s production of these devices is legitimate. In 2001, a breakthrough occurred when one of these devices (20 pts)",
        "factored 15 into 3 and 5. Integers could be factored in polynomial time on these devices by using (10 pts)",
        "Shor’s algorithm, which would render RSA encryption useless. For ten points, name these devices that could improve upon the binary nature of computers by using qubits."
      ],
      "answer": "quantum computers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This justice joked that the Supreme Court had the power to determine what golf is in his dissent in PGA Tour v. Martin. This man called a ruling against antisodomy laws a product of “law profession culture,” and he called the legalization of gay marriage a (20 pts)",
        "“naked claim to super-legislative power.” This justice wrote that the individual right to carry arms was guaranteed in the majority opinion in DC v. Heller, and he echoed Stephen Breyer in calling an Obamacare ruling “pure (10 pts)",
        "applesauce.” For ten points, name this originalist justice whose 2016 death caused a lengthy vacancy on the Supreme Court."
      ],
      "answer": "Antonin Scalia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was replicated in North Vietnam when two namesake journals were founded during the Nhan Van Giai Pham affair. This event was announced in the speech “On the Correct Handling of the Contradictions Among People.” It led to the (20 pts)",
        "Anti-Rightist Movement after the establishment of a “Democratic Wall” and the outpouring of thousands of hostile letters prompted (10 pts)",
        "Mao Zedong to prosecute its participants. For ten points, name this Chinese Communist campaign in which citizens were encouraged to criticize their government."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hundred Flowers Movement or Campaign, etc.",
        "Baihua yundong"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. The GIA, a group of Algerian terrorists, bombed this system in 1995, wounding 13 people at Maison Blanche. In 1903, 84 people died using this system, mostly in Couronnes [koor-own]. This system, which was inspired by (20 pts)",
        "Fulgence Bienvenu¨e, opened during the 1900 Universal Exposition. It features many Hector Guimard- designed entrances designed in the Art Nouveau style, and in 1930, it purchased a competitor run by the (10 pts)",
        "North-South Company, thus incorporating Line 13 from Saint-Lazare. For ten points, name this public transit system of the French capital."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Paris M´etro",
        "M´etro de Paris",
        "M´etropolitain",
        "descriptions of Paris’ subway system, and"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote in support of progressive politics in his Commoner magazine, and he noted that Christian values laid a foundation for group morality in his “Prince of Peace” speech, which he recited repeatedly on the (20 pts)",
        "Chautauqua circuit. Years before the Lusitania disaster prompted this man to resign as Woodrow Wilson’s secretary of state, this man supported (10 pts)",
        "bimetallism, proclaiming that “you shall not crucify mankind” in an 1896 convention speech. For ten points, name this Democratic presidential candidate who gave the “Cross of Gold” speech."
      ],
      "answer": "William Jennings Bryan"
    }
  ]
}